<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Pharisaism display'd, or Hypocrisie detected In a sermon preached in St. Mary's Church in Stamford, August the 21st, 1690. Being the triennial visitation of the right Reverend father in God, Thomas Lord Bishop of Lincoln. By George Topham, prebendary of Lincoln.</title>
            <author>Topham, George, d. 1694.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62952</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1907</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220704</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832096</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832096</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36565</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62952)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36565)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2100:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Pharisaism display'd, or Hypocrisie detected In a sermon preached in St. Mary's Church in Stamford, August the 21st, 1690. Being the triennial visitation of the right Reverend father in God, Thomas Lord Bishop of Lincoln. By George Topham, prebendary of Lincoln.</title>
                  <author>Topham, George, d. 1694.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Thomas Fox, at the Angel in Westminster-Hall; and are to be sold by Mr. Caldecot, bookseller, in Stamford, Lincolnshire,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Copy has print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hypocrisy --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36565:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>PHARISAISM DISPLAY'D, OR <hi>Hypocriſie Detected.</hi> IN A SERMON Preached in St. <hi>Mary</hi>'s Church in <hi>Stamford, August</hi> the 21ſt, 1690.</p>
            <p>Being the Triennial Viſitation of the Right Reverend Father in God, <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>LINCOLN.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>GEORGE TOPHAM,</hi> Prebendary of <hi>Lincoln.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Fox,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall;</hi> and are to be ſold by Mr. <hi>Caldecot,</hi> Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller, in <hi>Stamford, Lincoln-ſhire,</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:36565:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:36565:2"/>
            <head>PHARISAISM DISPLAY'D, OR Hypocriſie Detected, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> LUKE xii.</hi> v. <hi>i.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Beware ye of the leaven of the Phariſees, which is hypocriſie.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>REligion and a Holy Life is ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the making all Humane Societies Happy, that thereupon it has conſtantly been recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the wiſeſt Men, and greateſt Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers: The very Poet could obſerve this to his Country-men the <hi>Romans,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Dîs te minorem quòd geris,</l>
                  <l>Imperas;</l>
               </q> that they owed their Succeſs to their Piety, and were made Commanders of the World for their Obedience to their Gods.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:36565:3"/>
            <p>'Tis of ſuch concern for the eſtabliſhing Government, that all Law-givers have thought it neceſſary to prohibit the Violation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; and it carries ſo much of the Image of God in it, that all his Revelations to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs and Prophets, eſpecially that by the Bleſſed Jeſus to the Chriſtian Church, do mainly inſiſt upon it.</p>
            <p>When the Heathen World went greatly aſtray, by their abominable Idolatries, even in their pretended Religious Rites, the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Goſpel appear'd to turn them from the power of Satan unto God: And when the <hi>Jews</hi> (but chiefly the <hi>Phariſees</hi>) had ſo ſtrangely degenerated in their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and Practiſes, from the great Deſign of the Law, our Lord proteſts againſt them, and gives his Diſciples this caution, <hi>Beware ye of the leaven of the Phariſees, which is hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From which words I ſhall obſerve,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>First,</hi> Who theſe <hi>Phariſees</hi> were.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> What this Leaven of theirs was, which our Saviour cautions his Diſciples againſt.</item>
                  <item>And then, <hi>thirdly,</hi> Conſider how much of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:36565:3"/>this ſour Leaven is ſpread abroad a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, and give ſome Cautions againſt it.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> Who theſe <hi>Phariſees</hi> were:</p>
            <p>They were a particular Sect, proudly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting ſingular Opinions and Practiſes dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from the other <hi>Jews,</hi> and ſuch as were not enjoyn'd in the Law of <hi>Moſes:</hi> The Name <hi>Phariſee</hi> is to ſeperate and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide; and themſelves were diſtinguiſh'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſeveral ſorts, as the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Writers tell us.</p>
            <p>Some were called the <hi>Sechemitical Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees;</hi> theſe made a Trade of Religion, and all their pretended Sanctity, was one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to vail their inward Villanies, that ſo they might the more demurely Cheat. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were ſtyl'd the <hi>Stumbling Phariſees,</hi> who for an appearance of Humility, would ſcarce lift up their feet in the Streets. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers they called the <hi>Winking Phariſees,</hi> becauſe they ſhut their eyes as they paſt along, leaſt they ſhould (as they gave out) behold a Temptation. And others they ſtyl'd the <hi>Boaſting Phariſees,</hi> becauſe they pretended not only to do whatſoever the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:36565:4"/>Law required, but even to Works of Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>errogation, to perform a great deal more; and upon this account, boaſted that God himſelf rejoyced in them, and that they were infinitely dear to him.</p>
            <p>Yet if we may credit <hi>Joſephus,</hi> they did not withdraw themſelves from the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, or Temple publick Worſhip. Tho' concerning the Synagogue-Worſhip, there is probable Evidence, that the chief Sects among the <hi>Jews,</hi> and therefore the <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees,</hi> as one of them, had their diſtinct Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies: And 'tis certain, the <hi>Phariſees</hi> did reject the beſt of Men from their Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue-Communion, meerly for confeſſing <hi>that Jeſus was the Christ,</hi> and becoming his Diſciples. And in the Temple-Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip they were guilty of a kind of Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, under an appearance of Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for whereas the Daily Sacrifice in the Temple was a Burnt Offering, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore appointed for Expiation and Attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Devotions of thoſe who attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the Hours of Prayer and Sacrifice, ought to be conformable thereunto; but the <hi>Phariſees</hi> Prayer there, as our Saviour deſcribes it, had nothing in it of Humble
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:36565:4"/>Supplication for Mercy and Favour, <hi>but he thanks GOD that he was not as other men.</hi> And this Spirit of Diviſion was ſo much worſe in them, becauſe 'twas founded in a high conceit, and great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in their own Piety, when all the while there was nothing in it but Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie.</p>
            <p>Which brings me to the ſecond Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, what this Leaven of the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees</hi> was, which our Lord and Maſter cautionizes his Diſciples againſt: And this Leaven (as he Expounds himſelf) was of two ſorts; the Leaven of Corrupt and Superſtitious Doctrine, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. <hi>ver.</hi> 16. and here the Leaven of Hypocriſie: Now 'tis the nature of Leaven not onely to ſpread and diffuſe itſelf, but alſo to ſwell the Lump 'tis mixt with: ſo this Leaven of the <hi>Phariſees</hi> did ſour and imbitter their Minds, puff and fill them with Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, Cruelty, and Pride. Hypocriſie is an affectation of ſeeming to be what a Man is not, in point of Piety towards God, or Love and Charity towards Men; and at this Art, the <hi>Phariſees</hi> were ſubtile Maſters: Whenever they deſign'd to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36565:5"/>Orphans or Widdows Houſes, long Prayers, and Faſting twice a Week, muſt uſher in the Inhumane Villany. If any Covetouſneſs, or Cruelty of more than ordinary Size was to be committed, they preſently covered it with <hi>Corban,</hi> and were Deceivers of Men in the Name of God. Their Study was to be circumſpect and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in their Wickedneſs, <hi>Noctem peccatis &amp; fraudibus addere nubem;</hi> They ſinned out of ſight as much as might be, and made it their buſineſs only to appear unto Men to be Righteous: And therefore well might our Saviour give it in charge to his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, to beware of their Leaven or Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie. And becauſe he did ſo, I ſhall give ſome Inſtances wherein this their Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſaical Hypocriſie did conſiſt:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> They placed much Righteouſneſs in their being a peculiar Party, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining a kind of Separation, and pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a greater Holineſs and Devotion, an exacter Knowledge of the Law, and a more perfect Obedience to it, than any of the reſt of the People; and by theſe Pretences gain'd ſtrangely in the Opinion
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:36565:5"/>of the unthinking Rabble. Our Lord himſelf brings in the Phariſees openly boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a greater Piety, a ſtricter Life, a high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Righteouſneſs than any other ſort of Men. In the 18th of St. <hi>Luke, verſe</hi> 8. <hi>Two Men</hi> (ſays he) <hi>went up into the Temple to pray, the one a Phariſee, the other a Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican: The Phariſee ſtood, and prayed thus with himſelf; God, I thank thee, that I am not as other Men are, Extortioners, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt, Adulterers, or even as this Publican.</hi> Where we find him making a Diſtinction, between himſelf and other Men, in the very firſt words he ſpeaks to God. Yet for all this, if we obſerve the Character our Saviour gives of them, we ſhall find them ſo far from being better, that they were worſe than other Men; that thô they profeſt they were no Extortioners, yet they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd Widows Houſes, and that for all their pretended outward Sanctity, they were within full of Extortion and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Their Righteouſneſs did much conſiſt in ſuch a Zeal as was diſorderly, fierce, and cenſorious. They declar'd a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36565:6"/>great Reſpect to the Memory of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, but this was only to gain Credit to their own Dictates. Their Zeal was a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent eſpouſing the Intereſt of their own Errours, and was not ſo much for God and his Law, as for themſelves and their own Party. They were far more nice, far more ſcrupulous in leſſer things, than they were in thoſe of greateſt Moment, far more punctual in the Obſervance of their own Precepts and Inſtitutions, than thoſe that were of God's appointment. They were ſtrict in waſhing thoſe hands which remain'd polluted by Evil Works; and were careful to tythe Mint, Aniſe, and Cummin, but omitted the weightier Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Law. For what Law more Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred and Indiſpenſable, what more Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and Agreeable to Humanity, than that which requires us to Honour our Parents, to Relieve and Aſſiſt them in their Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities and Wants? Yet ſuch was the Blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Phariſees, that with reſpect to their unlawful Vow of <hi>Corban,</hi> they could without Regret diſpence with the Law of God, in not honouring their Parents.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:36565:6"/>
            <p>Another Inſtance of their Hypocriſie was, That they preſcrib'd to others what themſelves would not practiſe. They were forward in binding heavy Burdens on other Mens ſhoulders, but were not willing themſelves to ſtoop to the Duties of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection and Obedience. They were ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Friends to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> that by them the Queſtion was propounded, <hi>Whether it was lawful to give Tribute to him, or no?</hi> And were (as <hi>Joſephus</hi> relates) conſtantly diſaffected to their Governours, and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently Turbulent and Seditious; for they were of a haughty and proud Spirit, and ſcorn'd to pay Reſpect to any Rule or Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, without it carried the Impreſs of their own Invention, looking upon themſelves as the only Pious, and Favourites of Heaven, and therefore fit to manage all Affairs, both in Church and State. And when they had the Power in their Hands (notwithſtanding their pretended Humility and Mortification) none were more violent and bloody than they, as appears from their barbarous Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties under the Government of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and eſpecially in their being concern'd in proſecuting our Lord to death, and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:36565:7"/>after him with various methods of Cruelty, and particularly murdering <hi>James the Just,</hi> the firſt Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt inſtance I ſhall give of their Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, lay in their flaming Zeal to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelyte to their Party, to make Diſciples to their Sect, whilſt they made them worſe and not better, greatly more worſe than they were before: This our Saviour ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to them in the 23 of St. <hi>Matth.</hi> v. 13. <hi>Wo unto you Scribes and Phariſees, hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites; for ye compaſs ſea and land to make one Proſelyte, and when he is made, ye make him twofold more the child of hell then your ſelves.</hi> And ſo indeed they did, for the Proſelites made by theſe <hi>Phariſees,</hi> became much worſe than themſelves, the Scholars far out-did their Maſters in their wicked lives. This was obſerv'd by <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites (ſays he) that are made by you, do not only not believe, but do blaſpeme the Name of Chriſt twice as much as you your ſelves; the <hi>Gentile</hi> exceeds the <hi>Jew</hi> in his Unbelief.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:36565:7"/>
            <p>Thus having given ſome inſtances of the Hypocriſie of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> I ſhall now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to conſider how much of this ſower Leaven is ſpread abroad amongſt us, and give ſome Cautions againſt it: yet I ſhall not ſtrain Reſemblances to make the Caſes parallel, but only take notice of things as they really are, to obſerve how far there is a likeneſs to, or compliance with the Spirit of <hi>Phariſaiſm.</hi> And by the way give me leave to declare, that I cordially wiſh well to all Men of what Party or Perſwaſion ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever; and therefore whatever I ſhall ſay, that ſpeaks the Error or Danger of any of them, is not out of deſign to blacken or caſt reproach, but out of this true charitable end, to warn others to beware thereof: And for my part, I look upon it as my Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to ſpeak out; for whilſt the Sons of the Church of <hi>England</hi> were in purſuit of the Jeſuit, an unexpected Party came be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, and I am afraid, ſtill lies lurking to reward them with <hi>Joab</hi>'s Complement un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the fifth Rib. Do we not daily hear them beſpatter the pureſt Church in the Chriſtian World, revile her whole Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Diſcipline, and Service, traduce her
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36565:8"/>Clergy of every Rank and Order, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour by all Arts and Slanders, to poiſon the World again with their old Phariſaical Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of Sedition and Faction. Now ſhall we, whilſt the Papiſts on one hand call us Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, and charge us with Schiſm? and the Seperatiſts on the other hand (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding our late oppoſing the <hi>Romiſh</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, when we know who they were that readily joyn'd) charge us with Popery, and give our Worſhip the title of Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; be ſilent, bear the Charge, and not plead for ourſelves? God forbid; I ſhall therefore in as few words as I can, lay open the Leaven of both theſe Parties, and give ſome Cautions againſt it.</p>
            <p>And firſt for the Papiſts:</p>
            <p>Our Caſe with reſpect to that of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> is much like that of the Apoſtles, with regard to the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> for when they profeſſed the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, and Worſhipped God after the way which they unjuſtly called Hereſie, the <hi>Phariſees</hi> ſentenced them to be put out of the Synagogue: And Jeſus himſelf (as the <hi>Talmud</hi> of the <hi>Venice</hi> Edition, has been obſerv'd to affirm,) was excommunicated
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36565:8"/>with the <hi>Shammatha,</hi> or Great Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication: And becauſe we (as we ought) reject the Evil and Corrupt <hi>Romiſh</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines and Practiſes, which are all laid (<hi>Phariſee</hi> like) in Hypocriſie, to maintain their own Grandeur, and make good their <hi>Regalia Papae,</hi> they let flie their <hi>Anathema's</hi> in the various Canons of the Conventicle of <hi>Trent,</hi> and Annually (with all the Solemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of a proud and malicious Zeal) Curſe us in the Bull in <hi>Caenâ Domini.</hi> And tho' they at <hi>Rome</hi> keep to their publick Worſhip, as the <hi>Phariſees</hi> did, yet are they groſly guilty of Schiſm, by unjuſtly rejecting all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſtian Churches. And herein they paſs Sentance, as the <hi>Phariſee</hi> did againſt the <hi>Publican,</hi> upon thoſe who are much better than themſelves.</p>
            <p>And as 'twas one quality of the Leaven of the <hi>Phariſees</hi> to be fierce and cruel, for where they could not prevail by their Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, when they had any Credit or Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in the State, they made uſe of that (tho' after the moſt barbarous and inhumane manner) to proſelite to their Party. And do not the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> take the ſame Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods? Are not their chiefeſt Arguments
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:36565:9"/>drawn (where they have power) out of <hi>Bonner</hi>'s Logick, Fire and Faggot? Is it not by Bloody Inquiſitions, Maſſacres, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions; by horrid Treaſons and cruel Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies, that they propagate that their <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion?</p>
            <p>In ſhort, as the <hi>Phariſees</hi> of old, ſo the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> of late, put themſelves into all Garbs, and ſute themſelves to all Diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the better to proſelite to their Party; if to day they are full of Proceſſions, Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and Whippings, to morrow ſhall gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie them with Maſqueradings, Plays, and Jollity; if upon one Door there be an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, caſting down to Hell all Tranſgreſſors, upon another you'll-ſee a Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilee, or Pardon for all Tranſgreſſions; if on one ſide of the Street a Houſe of Vail'd Nuns, on the other, a Houſe of open Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſans: Their promiſing of Pardon of Sin, upon condition of Performances unneceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and inſufficient, ſuch as undertaking Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimages to the Shrines of Saints, Viſiting Churches, making War upon Infidels and Hereticks, contributing Money, repeating ſo many <hi>Ave Marie's</hi> and <hi>Pater Noſters,</hi> what are they but Religious Cheats? And thô
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:36565:9"/>they ſpare no pains, but compaſs Sea and Land to make one Proſelite; yet when he is made, (as our Saviour told the <hi>Phariſees</hi>) <hi>they make him twofold more the child of hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next that falls under my conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are our Diſſenting Parties at home; and 'tis ſtrange we ſhould have any ſuch at this time of day amongſt us; I know that the ſour Leaven of Diviſion was once deeply moulded into our Peoples breaſts, and they were envenom'd with an Opinion, <hi>That the Biſhops and Clergy, nay, all the Members of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>were Popiſhly affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</hi> and this Calumny how weak ſoever, was yet ſo unhappily ſtrong, as to carry off many well-meaning, but weaker Brethren from our Communion. But now that the Fathers and Sons of this Church, have given (eſpecially under the late Tryal) ſuch good aſſurance to the contrary, we hoped, (as juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we might) that theſe Miſ-repreſentations would eaſily have been ſeen through, and abhorr'd by all our Diſſenting Brethren; and that they would readily have come in, and joyn'd with us in one Publick Worſhip, and lent a helping hand to preſerve that Church which the common Enemy thruſt at with ſo
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:36565:10"/>much Malice and Envy: For if there were any ſuch Tincture of Popery, or Papiſtical Inclination in the Sons of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> have taught our Pretenders to a further Reformation to ſay and publiſh, why ſhould the Emiſſaries of <hi>Rome</hi> be more induſtriouſly intent upon our Deſtruction, than upon the Extirpation of all other Proteſtants in the World?</p>
            <p>Indeed the reaſon is, That the Church of <hi>England</hi> has for her Faith reſiſted to Blood; that this Church has ſent into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven whole Colonies of Confeſſors and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs for the Truth; that this Church has conſtantly (and of late as much as ever) maintain'd her own Cauſe, and the common Cauſe of all the Reformed Churches; that this Church is ſtill (thanks be to God, and their Sacred Majeſties) the Ornament and the Apology, the Support and the Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all the Proteſtant Churches through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the World: Our Brethren beyond the Seas cannot be rooted out with eaſe, or but perſecuted with ſafety, whilſt there is a Church of <hi>England</hi> to ſtand as a Rampire in the way between them and Ruine: but deſtroy or extinguiſh this Church, and all
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:36565:10"/>the Reformed Churches abroad, will ſoon be ſhatter'd and made a Prey: O that our Separatiſts were wiſe! that they underſtood this! that they would but conſider who they are actuated by: They little think that they are but Journy-men to their and our worſt Enemies the Jeſuites, who drive a Trade of Diviſions in Church and State, in hopes one day to ſacrifice them both to their Revenge and Avarice.</p>
            <p>Now there's nothing more diſhonourable to the nature of Man, or more to the ſhame of his underſtanding, than to be made ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Man's Property, or Tool; yet ſuch is the ſottiſhneſs of too many amongſt us, that notwithſtanding all the Arguments that have been us'd, they are ſtill reſolv'd to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reacht and abus'd by Men ingenuouſly wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, are ſtill as induſtrious Agents to ſpread abroad their Leaven of Separation, as ever. And therefore my Reverend Brethren, (with ſubmiſſion I ſpeak it) I think 'tis the Duty of every one of us, in our ſeveral Places and Cures, to Cautionize our People to be ware of them: And good reaſon we have for it, if we caſt but an eye about us, and ſee how zealous they are to proſelite to their ſeveral
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:36565:11"/>Parties, and how maliciouſly they Mis-figure us to the more weak and unwary, to draw them from our Communion. They cannot but acknowledge, (and ſome of the Ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaders of them have done it in print) that we have all the Fundamentals of the true Religion, both in reſpect of Faith and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe: We agree in all Eſſentials with all the Proteſtant Churches of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> as the <hi>Harmony of Confeſſions</hi> will ſatisfie every Man, who will be but at the pains to read them.</p>
            <p>We add no Articles of our own making to the <hi>Apoſtles Creed,</hi> (as we know who do) nor do we ſnip one of the <hi>Ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> and then ſlit another to make up the number: We do not equal the <hi>Apocrypha</hi> with the <hi>Canonical Scriptures,</hi> neither do we prohibit the Laity the conſulting thoſe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Records, but as much as in us lies, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to perſwade them to read and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate on them: We have but two Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, according to our Saviour's Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and our Publick Service is perform'd in our own Language: We do not buy or ſell Pardons, nor do we truſt in any Merits ſave thoſe of our moſt Bleſſed Redeemer Jeſus Chriſt: We pray for noue who are depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:36565:11"/>this Life, much leſs do we Invocate any of the Saints: We renounce the ſtrange Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Tranſubſtamiation, as we do all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions to Infallibility upon Earth. What pretence can they then have, not to joyn Communion with us? If ſome things indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and uncommanded in Holy Writ, do make them divide from us of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> they muſt (for the very ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) not only ſeparate from all the Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Churches of <hi>Europe,</hi> but from themſelves too, wherein ſome things muſt be indifferent.</p>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding all this, how pieviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are they bent againſt us? And out-run the <hi>Phariſees</hi> in the way of Separation; for thoſe, though they were for Prayers of their own, yet joyn'd in the Publick Prayers of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church; but theſe are ſo far from joyning with us in Prayer, that they cry out againſt our Publick Service, and condemn the Form, only becauſe 'tis Uniform: Yet were they not as Ignorant as they are Envious, and as ſtubbornly reſolved not to be Inform'd, as they are both, they might ſoon be ſatisfied, that ſet Forms of Prayer have been the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Practiſe of the Church of GOD in her Publick Worſhip, in all Ages, both <hi>Jew</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:36565:12"/>and Chriſtian. For as no Form of Prayer is the Mother of Confuſion, ſo ſeveral Forms by Perſons of the ſame Church, are the Means and Inlets of Diviſion: and therefore to prevent all Diviſions in the Church, and to avoid all ignorant, inſignificant, and extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant ways of expreſſing our Minds unto God in Prayer; as alſo that we might Communicate in each others Prayers, and reap the benefit of each others Fervency and Devotion, theſe were the great and weighty Reaſons wherefore a ſet and ſtanding Form of publick Prayer, has ever been preſcribed and uſed in the Church.</p>
            <p>Again, as the <hi>Phariſees</hi> of old were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly backbiting and ſpeaking Evil of the High-Prieſt, ſo our Modern <hi>Phnriſees</hi> make it a piece of their Religion, to beſpatter and ſlander, deſpiſe and contemn the Perſons and Commands of our Reverend Biſhops, whom they ought to ſerve and obey in the Lord; Epiſcopacy being an Apoſtolical Inſtitution, as appears from the Biſhops which they Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained in ſeveral Churches: And St. <hi>Jerom</hi> aſſures us, that 'twas the Judgment of the whole Chriſtian World in his time, (that for avoiding of Schiſm and Hereſies) it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:36565:12"/>there ſhould be one Biſhop in every Dioceſs.</p>
            <p>But to come nearer home, the Learned Doctor <hi>Du Moulin</hi> wrote a Book to Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the <hi>French</hi> Reformed Churches from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Pattern to any <hi>Scottiſh</hi> or <hi>Engliſh</hi> Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians to reject their Biſhops, where he gives us alſo the ſevere Cenſures of <hi>Zanchy</hi> and <hi>Calvin</hi> againſt thoſe who deny Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to their Lawful Biſhops a <hi>Teſter me Deo,</hi> ſays <hi>Zanchy, I protest before GOD and in my Conſcience, that I hold them no better than Schiſmaticks, who account it a part of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, to have no Biſhops in the Church.</hi> And ſays <hi>Calvin, They are worthy of any Execrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who will not ſubmit themſelves to that Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarehy, which ſubmitteth itſelf unto the LORD.</hi> And <hi>Calvin</hi> for his own part, though he had not the Title, had as much Authority as ever Biſhop of <hi>Geneva</hi> had; and Presbytery itſelf is little elſe than a Multiplied Epiſcopacy, ſetting up a Dioceſan in every Pariſh, only with the Addition of an Unparallelld Pride, and Inſolency into the Bargain. <hi>Beza</hi> the great Patron of Presbyterian Elderſhip, yet onfeſſes it to be neceſſary, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Presbyterio <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> eſſit, &amp; permaneret; That one be Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:36565:13"/>over the Presbytery;</hi> and this not <hi>pre tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore,</hi> but to continue; and allows St. <hi>Jerom</hi>'s Reaſon why it ſhould be ſo, <hi>In Remedium Schiſmatis;</hi> For the avoiding of Schiſm. And I hope this Age will not yet forget, that when the Reverend Biſhops were laid aſide, when the influences of thoſe Lights were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, what a Night of Darkneſs over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread the Face of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church; not unlike unto that which now threatens our <hi>Northern</hi> Brethren: for the ſame Arguments which the Presbyterians had fiercely uſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Biſhops, were by the Independants unanſwerably manag'd againſt themſelves: and then there ſucceeded more Sub-diviſions, the Anabaptiſt got up and bore Sway; the Fifth Monarchy Men made busſle for the Rule; and at laſt, up ſtarts the Quaker, and he'll hold forth to them all.</p>
            <p>Thus (though they could all but too well agree to Ruine the poor Church of <hi>England</hi>) yet no ſooner had they done that, which was, and ſtill is their Deſign, but you ſee how they fell out among themſelves about their particular Ends; and when they had pull'd down that which they maliciouſly call'd <hi>Babylon,</hi> the <hi>Engliſh Jeruſalem,</hi> their Language
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:36565:13"/>was ſo divided, that they could none of them build a <hi>Babel</hi> of their own.</p>
            <p>Thus Religion, whoſe main buſineſs and deſign is to perſwade Men to Unity, was generally made the occaſion of Quarrel; for no ſooner had they gone off from the peaceable and pious Ways of the Church, but into how many By-paths of Error did they run? and fled as faſt from one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as they did at firſt from us. And God knows this Leaven of Separation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins now to ſpread again as much as ever, and there are not wanting thoſe, who as boldly as impiouſly give out, that the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Spirit cannot be better kept than by Diſ-uniting; that is, (though they dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer amongſt themſelves) by uniting againſt the Eſtabliſhed Religion, and make that bleſſed Spirit whoſe Fruit is Peace, and Love, and Gentleneſs, the Author and Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menter of Diſcord and Strife, as if the fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Tongues, he appeared in, had been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd for Incendiaries, and the Zeal, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by thoſe ſacred Flames, could not be better expreſt, than in unkind Heats, and uncharitable Animoſities; and the ruſhing of the Wind, which filled the Room where
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:36565:14"/>the Diſciples were met, portended onely Storms and Tempeſts to the Chriſtian Church, and thoſe to be bred within her own Bowels.</p>
            <p>But to proceed; another piece of the Hypocriſie of the <hi>Phariſees</hi> was; in that their making long Prayers, and pretending to greater Mortification, Self-denial, and Contempt of the World, was only that they might the more eaſily and readily De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud the Widdows and Orphans; and at the ſame time that they pretended to ſcorn all Secular Intereſts, they were the moſt covetous Perſons living. And our home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred <hi>Phariſees</hi> do not only imitate, but have out-done the Copy: for though they cry themſelves up to be the great Lovers of the Life Eternal, yet if you mark them in their ſeveral Employs, and obſerve how they'll Equivocate and Lye to gain their Ends, and advance their Intereſts, you'll ſee that they prefer the Temporal, and that Gain is their Godlineſs; and that though they give out, they are all upon the ſpur to the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> are yet for all their haſt, (if they had the power in their hands) as ready to make a Halt again in Church Lands as ever.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:36565:14"/>
            <p>Again, as the <hi>Phariſees</hi> of old boaſted a greater Tenderneſs of Conſcience than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Men, when all the while 'twas but Hypocriſie; for though they ſtrein'd at a Gnat, they had a Conſcience ſo wide as to ſwallow a Camel: So our Modern Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots, though they are ſo tender as to ſcruple at a Ceremony, yet they have a Conſcience ſo tough as to bear a Schiſin. They are no Sabbath-Breakers or Swearers, (for thoſe are Sins of no Profit) nor are they ordinarily drunk with Wine, without it be at another Man's charge, for that's both a diſgraceful and a coſtly Sin; but they are ſerious demure in all their Projects, and ſeek the Ruine of a Church in as great Sobriety, as <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> did that of a Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>Another part of the Religion of the <hi>Phariſees</hi> lay in deriding the Perſons, and cenfuring the Faults of other Men: And does it not paſs (with ſeveral of our Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiſts) for a very confiderable piece of Religion, to ſpeak contemptuouſly of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to ſcorn a Prieſt, deride a Biſhop, and mock a whole Profeſſion. This is the Piety of too many of them, this is their
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:36565:15"/>Religion, and this is the thing for which they ſo highly prize themſelves; and if they ſhould be denied this, if they ſhould be ſtript (as 'tis fit they ſhould) of their Zeal in ſcorning thoſe they ought to value, if all that Heat which appears in them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Perſons of other Men were quencht, all that ſour Leaven of theirs caſt out, they would have very little to ſay for their being of any Religion: For if their Faith be obſerv'd by their Works, ſuch as Patience, Humility, and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, thoſe Graces wherein the Kingdom of GOD conſiſts, you'll find them (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out breach of Charity) far from being what they imagine themſelves to be, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, truly Pious. Nay, 'tis now become (ſuch is the Age we live in) a main part of the Religion of ſome, firſt to invent and forge Lyes concerning the Perſons and Lives of thoſe who will not joyn with them in their Separation, and then with the greateſt Phariſaical Demureneſs, ſpread and report them for Truths. And they are ſo far from accuſing themſelves for this, that they applaud themſelves in it, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of looking upon themſelves to be
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:36565:15"/>worſe, (which I am ſure every good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ought to do) they believe themſelves to be better Men for ſo doing.</p>
            <p>Again, as the <hi>Phariſees</hi> when ever they had the Power in their hands, were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly cruel and bloody, ſo we have not forgot, how when our Saints in Buff had the Sword in hand, and their Blaſphemous Teachers ſuch Texts as this in their mouths, <hi>To bind their Kings in chains, and their Nobles with links of iron,</hi> how many Loyal Heads they brought to the Block; and to fill up their Inhumane Cruelty (true <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee</hi> like) they murdered the beſt of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and the Thirtieth of <hi>January</hi> will for ever bluſh in our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Kalender, as well as the Fifth of <hi>November.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> The <hi>Phariſees</hi> were a proud and ſelf-conceited Sect: And for our home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred Separatiſts, notwithſtanding their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhow of Humility, they are inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly full of Pride; and of this take one In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance for all: Can there be a greater piece of Pride, than for a Perſon of very low Parts, and little Learning, of contempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Education, and ſmall Improvements, to ſeparate from a Great and Admired Church,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:36565:16"/>the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and from the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions of the ſame in her Publick Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies, all contrived by the Wiſdom, direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Learning, embraced by the Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Eſtabliſhed by the Authority of ſuch a Nation, Confirmed by many Acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and by as many Convocations, or Repreſentatives of the Clergy, Sign'd and Seal'd by the Sufferings of many Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors and Martyrs, I ſay, for an Audacious Schiſmatick full of nothing but Ignorance, to ſcorn or pitty all his Teachers, as Fools and Blind, is ſuch an Arrogance, Self-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitedneſs, and Pride, as no Rhetorick can expreſs, no Charity excuſe, no Humility not cenſure.</p>
            <p>Thus do our Modern Separatiſts run pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel with the old <hi>Phariſees;</hi> And give me leave to tell you, (my Reverend Brethren) that 'tis the Duty of every one of us, to Caution the People committed to our Care and Charge, to beware of their Leaven: I know Prudence is to be conſulted how to reprove Diſſenting Brethren, but Courage and Reſolution is never to be laid aſide, and the more prevalent and reſolute any
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:36565:16"/>Party is, the more need of Courage to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it. Let them but once ſhew ſome true ſigns of their Repentance for what is paſt, by joyning Communion with us, and no Men living ſhall rejoyce more than we. But if inſtead of this, they ſtudy to raiſe their old Devil of Sedition again in the likeneſs of a Prophet, are ſtill as active to ſpread abroad their ſour Leaven, and are ſtill as induſtrious to proſelite eaſie natur'd Men to their Faction as ever: ſhall we be ſo cowardly and treacherous to that Church of which we have the honour and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, not only to be Members but Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters too, as not to tell our People (for all their coming <hi>in Nomine Domini</hi>) that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is but Hypocriſie, and endeavour (as much as in us lies) to lay open their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions, that they may not be twice poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon'd (by theſe Mountebanks in Divinity) in leſs than one Age.</p>
            <p>And for you my worthy Brethren of the other Cloth, I hope a few Motives will perſwade you to beware, eſpecially if you pleaſe to remember, into what a ſad Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion this Leaven of Hypocriſie once mould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this flouriſhing Church and Nation: For
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:36565:17"/>what things are there in Holy Writ (how Eſſential ſoever to Chriſtianity) which have not been queſtion'd and diſputed, if not denied and rejected, ſince this ſour Leaven has been ſpread abroad amongſt us? 'Tis to this alone we owe the raging of the Sea, and the roaring of the Waves, whereby the Madneſs of the People is oft expreſt: 'Twas this Leaven of Schiſm, made Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and a Sale of the Crown-Lands, and Murdered GOD's Anointed in order to it; but for this we had never heard either of Plunder or Sequeſtration, the ſound of thoſe Names had not reacht our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ears: In ſhort, to this alone we owe the Legion not only of Creeds of Dogmatizings here amongſt us, (ſince the Year 41. in eſpecial manner) but even of Skepticiſm, Apoſtaſie, and Atheiſm.</p>
            <p>And now to conclude, (for I fear I have been too tedious) with a word or two to our Separating Brethren, and I heartily wiſh that I were but as able, as from the bottom of my Soul I am willing, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them to joyn with us in the Publick Worſhip of God: One would think our
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:36565:17"/>common Enemies ought to make them our Friends, and 'twould certainly do it, if they would but permit themſelves either in Piety or Prudence to be provoked by them to Emulation: For if all ſorts of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, even the <hi>Sorboniſts,</hi> and the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> the <hi>Dominicans,</hi> and the <hi>Franciſcans,</hi> how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever differing in Opinions, and burning in Heats one againſt another, do yet agree a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Proteſtants, what ſhould hinder all ſorts of Proteſtants, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (however divided in Opinions) from meeting together, and agreeing in the ſame Church of <hi>England,</hi> whoſe Reformation is made Authentick by the higheſt Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty under Heaven? But if they will not come in, if they will not caſt out this Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of theirs, but are ſtill reſolved (let what Arguments as will be uſed) to be peeviſhly bent againſt us; yet we'll Treat them with Candor and Charity, and not ceaſe to Pray to GOD for them, and humbly beſeech him (for the ſake of his Deareſt Son, and our and their Bleſſed Saviour) in his due time, to heal all our Diviſions, and make up all our Breaches, that ſo we may Serve him with one Mind
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:36565:18"/>and one Mouth, to the Glory of his Holy Name, the Good of his Church, the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Their Sacred Majeſties, and the Peace and Proſperity of the Nation, which He of his Infinite Goodneſs grant.</p>
            <closer>
               <hi>Now to God the Father, to God the Son, and to God the Holy Ghost, be aſcrib'd, as is most due, all Glory, Honour, and Praiſe, both now and for ever.</hi> Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
